[SPEAKER_01]: Can you describe the nature of the relationship between you and your own mind, the citta, in any other way than what we have been describing it so far?
[SPEAKER_01]: Your own terms, your own descriptions, your own designations, and then we can see what comes out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you set an island.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you're doing things in order to find fulfillment,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a bit like being lost in like an ocean, in the sense of it's endless.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no end to that direction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, in contrast to that, the other direction, it's always there.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's always in the stable ground.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, that's what one sutra says.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, and I suppose that also that contrast, in the sense of there being this stable ground, as opposed to like drowning, like this, when you see that you're doing it for the animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I'm using the animal again.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're doing it
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you're not doing it for finding accomplishment there.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're doing it to... to attain, to... to establish yourself upon.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, to clarify, yeah, to... for that clarity.
[SPEAKER_03]: That clarity is the thing which means that you're not drowning.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the... it means that you're... you're... like, no matter what happens, there is...
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, safety in the sense that, yeah, I'm not going to, yeah, to go towards those things that I go...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what's... what would be another way of describing that withdrawal from multiplicity?
[SPEAKER_03]: Unification or composure.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it would be that unifying of the mind in a sense of, well, in a sense of composure, in a sense of samādhi, which again, you know, as we repeat millions of times, it's not the result of concentration, it's a result of withdrawal from the multiplicity.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, in the book that talks about the sutras, the perceptions of diversity would have subsided
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's established upon the perception of unity, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: the perception of that one gatheredness of an elevated space, or a safe space, or a space that does not partake to the ocean.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that space is constantly being bombarded by the hindrances, by your own thoughts, and then by your own... depending on how you attend to your own thoughts that are coming up, is whether that space would be
[SPEAKER_03]: So, there are varying degrees to which that clarity is, I mean...
[SPEAKER_03]: Absolutely, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: There is more and more and more.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the safety begins with the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the safety.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you might feel relatively safe before that, but the fact is that you could... that you still could swim along with the hindrances, if you're careless, means you're not truly safe-safe.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the waves could still pick you up from the shore and drag you back in.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, like, one shouldn't get complacent.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: I saw it as looking after my little sister.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, there was that similar kind of pressure and irresponsibility that you have.
[SPEAKER_02]: You feel this thing looking at you, learning from you, you know, and you've got to... Mirroring everything you do.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, she's just, you know, she's my sister.
[SPEAKER_02]: She's not my child.
[SPEAKER_02]: But I'm still responsible, you know, she's still learning, she's still looking at me, at my every move.
[SPEAKER_02]: So it's like,
[SPEAKER_02]: And so, you know, a lot of parents are...
[SPEAKER_02]: So, it's the relationship that I'm feeling that it's a good description of.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's the parent and child.
[SPEAKER_02]: And, you know, because of that pressure that a parent would feel the responsibility, I think that's why a lot of people just ignore, you know, kind of ignore their minds and don't want to just... don't want to look there, don't want to see what it's doing, don't want to take responsibility.
[SPEAKER_02]: And that's why a lot of children get abandoned.
[SPEAKER_02]: In the in the world, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, I think it's the same kind of relationship, really.
[SPEAKER_02]: That of... because the child's mind is malleable, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: It can be shaped.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, that mind can be shaped.
[SPEAKER_02]: And it can be like 10 years, 20 years, but it still has that nature of being able to be shaped.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, even though it's encrusted with whatever, with habits and so on, you can still shape it, unlike a... Yeah, it always remains the mind of a child, in that way, yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: But, unless it matures, finally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for that, you need to mature.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, and only maturity is a giving up of sensuality, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in the suit of this... Because that's what keeps it childish, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: And if it hasn't got to that point, well...
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, another good aspect of that simile is that, see, you know a child is not you, like a parent obviously, you know, is knowing I'm not my child, but at the same time cannot not identify with his child, with their child.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's impossible not to.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the relationship between you and your citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, even, as I said, people with zero, like, taming, or restraint, or withdrawal, do have a sense of, oh, you know, heart wants what heart wants, type of thing, or, you know, like, you can't help, but, like, my mind can't help I want this, or not want that, I'm just, like, I can't do anything about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, they're aware it's a separate thing,
[SPEAKER_01]: from their own decision-making capacities, that often overrides their own decisions and reason, even if they tell themselves, well, I know this is bad for me, but I can't stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But at the same time, there is absolutely no recognition of any other way of relating with it, other than identification.
[SPEAKER_01]: Heart wants what heart wants, but that's mine, heart.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I am that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they would often prioritize
[SPEAKER_01]: See, for example, say... say a reason tells you, oh, that's bad for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I've been thinking about it, I've been reflecting on it, and it's like, I really need to give this up.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you still have, your citta still craves for it, because it's still under the habit, under the influence, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people would experience that conflict, they would experience that discrepancy, but they would take the chitter side as more real than the reason side.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it would be like, I know it's bad, but the fact that there is still this craving means I am the one who wants it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why then they sort of remain conflicted and remain going back to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is like the nature of any addiction, obviously.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, actually, there is no reason for you to emphasize what citta wants more than what your reason tells you, except not wanting to endure the pain of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, a screaming child screams to get what he wants, and you can't bear it because emotionally you think you're torturing it, or scarring it, or you must... and then you're just under the pressure of its screams, and then you give in.
[SPEAKER_01]: And now, you convey the message that that's how it will get what it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll just pressure you and scare you more until you give me what I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, I'll leave you alone until there's something else that I want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you're never really alone.
[SPEAKER_01]: You become enslaved, simply by not wanting to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where that identification will be coming from as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not wanting to deal with it, by giving into it, you basically start overlooking it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, although you know it's not,
[SPEAKER_01]: You who really wants this, who... because I know it, but I don't really want it, I hate it, but there is still craving for it, you still go back to it, and you still think it's you who is doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, you are just the one giving in to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why without the sense restraint first, having been practiced, to contain it, there is no amount of
[SPEAKER_01]: Insight or reason that will make you prevail, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: First, you just need to have a hard no to the unwholesome things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so if a parent is not setting an example to their own child with their own behavior, no amount of telling their child how to behave would... would convey the right message, because
[SPEAKER_01]: They first see how you're behaving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can be saying one thing, but if you're doing another, that's what they're going to see.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same with citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could be trying to reason.
[SPEAKER_01]: Wishing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you still want and act out and not even experience that conflict between, hold on, I don't want this, but there is craving for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what needs to be undone.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're just going along with it, because you prefer the path of less resistance,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, well, that is the message you're conveying.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you can say, no, no, no, stop.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's obvious you don't really mean it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because otherwise, you would make the effort to stop.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that also, like, kind of... creates kind of an incoherent pattern for the mind, because it's... you say yes, you say no, but anyway you give in, so you cannot learn anything at some point.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, then it's basically the mind learns that it doesn't matter what you say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you'll give in to the pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not taking you seriously, exactly what a child would do.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can be shouting at it, but it sees what you really mean, because the way you behave.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, it's not going to take you seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: First time, maybe it was scared, but then it realized, nah, this is just noise.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, it learns how to do what it wants to do.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like that example you gave with the
[SPEAKER_05]: Learning to... how to convey a message to it is not in this sort of direct, I'll just tell it this.
[SPEAKER_05]: What it sees is what you do.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, like, in the example you gave, it was more direct.
[SPEAKER_05]: It was like, you can be speaking all of this, but what it's picking up on is your body language.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, you can be telling your citta to not resist, to unresist, to give up craving, while you're craving for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, what do you think citta will be doing then?
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to stop craving for it yourself.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, it's impressionable.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's like, through your actions.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you can tell your kid to, you know, work hard in their life.
[SPEAKER_02]: You know, smoking, playing video games, and telling your child, you know... To take life seriously and work hard.
[SPEAKER_02]: Don't become like me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_02]: That's exactly what's going to happen, you know.
[SPEAKER_02]: But then, you're working hard, you're showing that, and you're just picking that up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: Eventually, he does the same, you know.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's exactly like you want your citta to turn away from sensuality, from your will, from hindrances, from things that cause it suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to turn away from it first.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to stop giving in.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to stop delighting in it yourself, relishing it, wishing for it, planning it, craving for it, and then citta can eventually get the message as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: Any other?
[SPEAKER_01]: This side of the room?
[SPEAKER_04]: I was kind of struggling to come up with something.
[SPEAKER_04]: I've always kind of seen the mind as this kind of very vague,
[SPEAKER_04]: So, at first, when you came up with a wild animal simile, it was a bit... it's as if it was too, kind of, too palpable for me.
[SPEAKER_04]: It was too, like, almost too relatable, maybe.
[SPEAKER_04]: Solid.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_04]: But...
[SPEAKER_04]: But also, in a way, it was quite nice, because it's as if it creates space between... Oh, yeah, for sure.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...yourself and... Because that's the necessary step, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, say, like, what we just talked about the child, the example of that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the main reasons a person... a parent would not be disciplining their child or teaching the right things, even if they know they should,
[SPEAKER_01]: is because they're overly, basically, personally identified with it, and with its feelings, and with its moods, or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like that makes you lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, see, I know reasonably that saying no to my child
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be a good thing for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be beneficial for them.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, I will also feel their pain when I say that to them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, I can't say it because, to me, avoiding that pain is more important.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's just too personified, too personally involved, and you lose perspective on account of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You recognize, no, this is factually for my welfare and for its welfare.
[SPEAKER_01]: Otherwise, we're both done.
[SPEAKER_01]: Recognizing that space... Oh, no, no, it's like...
[SPEAKER_01]: I have a say in this.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, I would have a say in raising a child or taming a wild animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: And although, technically, it's still optional, you don't have to do it, you don't have to do anything, you realize, well, it's pretty much the least optional thing, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you think in terms of what's beneficial for you and for the animal in the long run,
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like, this is the only thing that they would qualify for beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything else is secondary to that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, like people would not see that space in between.
[SPEAKER_01]: They would not see...
[SPEAKER_01]: They would be either too identified with it, too mystified,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, my mind, it's this great entity.
[SPEAKER_01]: Too personally involved, in the same sense you would be with your child, all of that results in a loss of perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Perspective that would be revealing the danger of that situation.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like the cow herd simile in the Sutta.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, if the person responsible for keeping an eye on the cows while they're grazing,
[SPEAKER_01]: If someone forgets that they're going to beat him and imprison him, if the cows go and eat other people's fields, he won't pay attention to where they eat and what they do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And most people choose to forget those things because, well, it seems optional.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's how it presents itself.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because there is no immediate punishment that you feel.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you do, you don't make the association between the two.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then also, because, see, like, if I live under a constant threat, or if I could get in trouble, well, that's very unpleasant for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not a nice state of mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And plus, these animals are now agitated, because I don't let them eat what they want.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, as I said, naturally, a person would choose a path of less resistance, and then the debt and the punishment will accumulate, and when it comes, you will have nothing but to just cry about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: With the simile of, like, your sister, there's also, like, that we were talking on Telegram about, like, how, you know, the otherness of of the mind is like the otherness of people in, like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Sunny Lezda.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Slightly less.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you are still... Well, you don't want to personify it, because it's not a full person.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want to just think, oh, it's just another person, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it isn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the same sense, a young child, it's like, as he was saying, it's... it's... it's... the mind is still malleable.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like a full personality.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could personify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could give it more than it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the fact is,
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's another person, it kind of becomes like a complete thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, the way people relate with each other, it's like, well, I'm I, you're you, you do your thing, I do my thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Same.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, my mind has its own mind, it does its own, I'll do my own thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's the child or the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's... you can't have that degree of independence as you would from another person.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why I was saying before, in the previous talk, it's important to not overly personify it.
[SPEAKER_01]: On the other hand, you don't want to under-personify it either, saying, oh, it's just chemical brain processes in response to stimuli and has no consciousness of its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, well, it does, because it makes its own choices, obviously, that you're pressured by.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, there is that degree of autonomy of citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you add too much to it, you won't see it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you take away too much from it, you won't see it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, again, the goal is to tame the child, or teach it rightly, or tame the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're overly emotionally invested, you will not... you will lose perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, if you just say, well, I wash my hands of you,
[SPEAKER_01]: You do your own thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, you might feel freer for that period of time, but factually, the goal of training that child is not complete.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the opposite.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can't really just, just, okay, well, I'll just do my thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: You go on your own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not with your citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can do that with other people.
[SPEAKER_01]: But with your citta, no, you're just going to stay where you are, and the result of that attitude will be you're not aiming it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is it where, like, the kind of ascetic practice come from, like, this kind of
[SPEAKER_00]: Wanting to push citta away and...
[SPEAKER_01]: Pretty much, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Have a clean cut through all of this, so it doesn't even have to come up, so I don't have to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: The... those austere self-mortification practices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes, doing such practices in relation to citta can be beneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why Buddha said, well, let those who want to do those austere practices, do them.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not make them mandatory, because it will actually result in, oh, okay,
[SPEAKER_01]: I'll stick to this.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't see my mind anymore.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not my problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, it remains your problem.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're just ignoring it now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes it will be even sort of counterintuitive even to your own values.
[SPEAKER_05]: Very much so.
[SPEAKER_01]: When it comes to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Clarifying and outlining mind rightly, as I said, you shouldn't be overly emotionally invested, but you shouldn't be trying to get rid of it or sort of dismiss it either.
[SPEAKER_01]: And sometimes, in order to do neither of those things, you realize, oh, so what?
[SPEAKER_01]: I just have to eat milk porridge now, like a householder.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: By any ascetic, by any self-respecting sort of summoner, that's not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then the Buddha realized, well, actually, it's not about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not about where my values are currently.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's about direct input from the mind, from the citta.
[SPEAKER_01]: How does this... And then he realized, oh, if I don't do this, I will not be able to train it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the mind is too weak.
[SPEAKER_01]: Too invisible, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Too beaten down by everything else he was doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, that's, again, that's what's saying, like, and even in the suttas, the Buddha would often, when he came to these ascetic practices, and how much, and where is the line, he said, well, you realize the line, you have the broad line, things never to be done, obvious, the eight precepts, and so on, but then all this other was, like, he was dependent on where the mind was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes eating milk, rice, will obscure your mind, depending on where your intention was.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sometimes it will reveal it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Depending on where your intention to not eat it was.
[SPEAKER_01]: But for that, you need to see the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the reference.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when you have that reference, then you can train happily day and night.
[SPEAKER_01]: As they say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you realize, oh, this is the input.
[SPEAKER_01]: No external.
[SPEAKER_01]: How can you do that?
[SPEAKER_01]: That's not right.
[SPEAKER_01]: You shouldn't be doing that.
[SPEAKER_01]: You shouldn't be eating rice.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, and that's exactly what his former friends and companions, they were disgusted with him.
[SPEAKER_01]: He reverted to luxury.
[SPEAKER_01]: And they left him.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, if he was caring about that, about his peers approving of him, he would have never become the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: If he was caring about the tradition that he's been following, established culture, he would have never become the Buddha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because none of that has a mind as a reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just circumstantial involvement of everything and nothing, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why I keep saying, like, you know,
[SPEAKER_01]: The framework is the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everything within that, if it's tighter or looser, well, that should be determined individually, every single time, on the basis of where your mind is and why you're doing it for.
[SPEAKER_05]: I think, yeah, it's good to emphasize as well, like, every single time.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because even, let's say, milk, rice, the same thing, it's very so easy to say, oh,
[SPEAKER_05]: I find I always want this particular thing.
[SPEAKER_05]: I'll just give it up.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's much harder to notice that on some days, it can be rooted in craving and pressure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Then you don't do it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And on another occasion, or actually, it's not.
[SPEAKER_05]: And
[SPEAKER_05]: Now, you should actually allow it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: But I still won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And people would fall into that trap, like, yeah, but it doesn't matter, thus I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it doesn't really matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, well, it's true, but see, you could say the same in reverse.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't really matter, so why don't you do it?
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't really matter, so I won't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it just becomes a justification to just keep tightening, and tightening, and tightening, out of some, as I said, perceived sense of duty.
[SPEAKER_05]: It forces you to, like,
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that forces you to raise your child properly.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just, oh, he was fine eating this yesterday, I can just give it to it today without having to look at it or think about it.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's exactly what it becomes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or, he wasn't fine eating yesterday, thus I will keep forbidding it because, again, it's easier to just adhere to the view now that came out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could reasonably recognize every single time where intentions are rooted.
[SPEAKER_01]: What state of the child is it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it unruly, crying, screaming, having a fit to get what he wants?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: If it isn't, and now it's maybe even a bit depressed or something, okay, give it now to loosen up a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: Within, as I said, what was defined as the eight precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't go past that line, that's too much.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's a constant work, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: You constantly have to keep an eye on it, then.
[SPEAKER_01]: You constantly have to be checking in and monitoring which way it takes, and that's just too cumbersome.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because at the same time, I have this view offered now, that if I just keep
[SPEAKER_01]: This has a rule to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be the same effect, minus me having to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the point is, it won't have the same effect.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not learning.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not learning, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the the simile of the of the deer herd.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, when
[SPEAKER_01]: When the group of ascetic recognized, oh, yeah, this is all the bait and Mara's snare, so they shun the bait, go on the mountain, say no to everything, and then they begin to starve, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: And when they do return to stuff to eat, they still don't distinguish where the bait is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So they get, again, trapped by Mara.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, the final deer herd was the one that learned how to eat around the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: Every single time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not to eat it unwarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, every single time, the reference point should be the state of your citta, for whether to act or not act, whether it's beneficial, whether it's unbeneficial.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the whole training in a nutshell, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: The whole practice of jhāna, it's exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just taming the citta rightly, not choking it and asphyxiating it, and not letting it run loose.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until it's basically stabilized on the safe ground and it recognizes that.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's... the result is citta viveka.
[SPEAKER_01]: Viveka from the unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the pulls, from the pressures, from the hindrances, from the obstructions.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when the Buddha says in the Sutta, go monks and practice jhāna, that's what he means.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't mean go monks and do some meditation technique.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it would be at the end of such suttas.
[SPEAKER_01]: See, they would talk about the sutta about purifying your mind, not giving in to unwholesome states, instruct the monks in all these details, and then tell them, okay, now you heard this, now go and do the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: If jhāna was something completely different from that, he wouldn't have said it at the end of that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you realize, at the end of different contexts of types of purification and how to attend to things, he would address going now and do the jhāna.
[SPEAKER_01]: Do the jhāna basically means do this mind training on account of this context I'm providing you.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why it was unique to him, unique to the Buddhist practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's where exactly the results in overcoming the five hindrances, when the unruly child becomes fully disciplined, understanding, seeing for itself what's good for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the wild animal is fully tamed, obedient, pretty much knows what you think, without even having to do it, to say it, to tell it to do.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you both live happily.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's like the pleasant abiding here and now.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only thing that can disturb that, is if you start carelessly going back to sights, sounds, smells, tastes, touches, like this, so to say, that then, indirectly, start disturbing the animal again, because it wasn't completely... well, it wasn't completely freed.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to calm it, withdraw it from the unwholesome, stabilize it on the elevated, safe ground, the island, but then protect it there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't think now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you will think, oh, I can relax now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's true, you can relax.
[SPEAKER_01]: But not in regard to the bait.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can relax in regard to the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: But don't forget the bait is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, although you can probably handle it more than you used to, you are still grabbing onto the hooks and traps unnecessarily.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that is agitating the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe not as much as it used to, but it's still agitating it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there's absolutely no reason to do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's the priority thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why the thoroughbred will never be alone from the horse trainer.
[SPEAKER_01]: He can't get rid of the horse trainer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Initially, he might think or assume that the safety would be... the greatest safety would be if there is no horse trainer.
[SPEAKER_01]: He has to come to terms to accept that he'll never be alone from the horse trainer.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only way out from the whip of the horse trainer is to tame his behavior, not remove the horse trainer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's... and same like in the reverse order simile we gave, it's like the animal is watching you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is basically seeing only what you do.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in that sense, you're never wrong from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's why you can never be yourself fully.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you're always undermined by the other.